<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true reporte of the seruice in Britanie. Performed lately by the honorable knight Sir Iohn Norreys and other captaines and gentlemen souldiers before Guingand Together with the articles which the Prince D'ombes accorded to the defendants of the towne.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18655</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113298</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848534</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848534</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13634</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08323)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13634)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 326:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true reporte of the seruice in Britanie. Performed lately by the honorable knight Sir Iohn Norreys and other captaines and gentlemen souldiers before Guingand Together with the articles which the Prince D'ombes accorded to the defendants of the towne.</title>
                  <author>Montpensier, Henri de Bourbon, duc de, 1573-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn VVolfe, and are to be sold at his shop right ouer against the great south-doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Norris, John, --  Sir, 1547?-1597.</term>
               <term>Montpensier, Henri de Bourbon, --  duc de, 1573-1608.</term>
               <term>Guingamp (France) --  History --  Siege, 1591 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Henry IV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13634:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:13634:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
            <p>THE TRVE Reporte of the ſeruice in <hi>Britanie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Performed lately by the Honorable Knight Sir Iohn Norreys and other Captaines and Gentlemen ſouldiers <hi>before Guingand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with the Articles which the Prince <hi>D'ombes accorded to the defendants of the Towne.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>fleur-de-lis</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Iohn VVolfe, and are to be ſold at his ſhop right ouer againſt the great South-doore of Paules. 1591.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13634:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:13634:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>The true report of the ſeruice in Britanie, performed lately by the Honourable</hi> Knight Sir <hi>IOHN NORREYS</hi> and other Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and gentlemen ſouldiers before Guingand: toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the articles which the Prince D'ombes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the defendants of the towne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Marſhall man principally deuoteth him ſelfe to hazard his lims and life in the ſeruice of his Prince &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie for honour and crownes: as it were ſhame to eclipſe him the one, ſo it is iniurie to ſcant him the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for the ſureſt whetſtone of valour and vertue is renowne and glorie: in defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſouldier of his pay, you cut his purſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate his edge: in deprauing his honour, you cut his throate and ſtrike him ſtone deade: whereby I was induced to publiſh the renowned ſeruice done late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by that honourable knight S. IOHN NORREYS in Britanie: to the end that neither he, neither the reſt of the braue Captaines, gentlemen and ſouldiers ſhould want their due commendation, that both they may be encouraged to continew their braue &amp; heroicall mindes, and others inclined to aduance themſelues to the like honorable attempts &amp; actions. I am the better able to performe this my promiſe by reaſon of a letter I receiued thence from a gentleman ſo well qualified, that neither he wanted skill or wit to record the ſeruice with the pen, neither valour &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:13634:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->courage to performe anie enterpriſe with the ſword, being a principall actor in the execution thereof, the copie wherof I preſent to the reader, that he may be truely enformed of the ſeruice, and yeelde the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors their due commendation.</p>
            <p>SIR, by my laſt letters I aduertiſed you of the ſafe ariuall of our armie in Britanie, the third of May, continewing about the Abbay of Beauport a weeke, for the arming of the ſouldiers, mounting the artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie and marſhaling our Campe. The tenth, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan our march, and lodged with our troupes before <hi>Guingand</hi> the 13. Since which time, through the wonderful paines and continuall trauel of Sir IOHN NORREYS our L. Generall, the towne is rendered to the Prince D'OMBES, ſonne to the Duke MOM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PENSIER of the houſe of <hi>Burbon,</hi> Gouernour of Britainie for the King. The reporte whereof may ſeeme ſtraunge to you, for we our ſelues do wonder at it, conſidering the ſtrength of the place by arte and nature, and how greatly the conſeruation therof imported <hi>Philibert Emanuel, Duke Mercurie</hi> of the houſe of <hi>Vaudemont</hi> a collaterall branch of <hi>Lorrayne,</hi> Gouernour of Britanie for thoſe rebellious Leaguers who murthered his brother in law the late king his owne ſiſters husband: as well in regarde of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reputation, as of his profit and peculiar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, the towne being his proper inheritance, in the right of his wife <hi>Marie</hi> daughter and heire to <hi>Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Duke of <hi>Pontheiure,</hi> whoſe father <hi>Francis Vicount
<pb facs="tcp:13634:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->Martigues</hi> of the houſe of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> attained large territories in Britanie, marrying <hi>Charlotte</hi> ſiſter and heire of <hi>Iohn de Broſse</hi> who deſcended of the houſe of <hi>Ponthieure</hi> a collateral line of the Dukes of Britanie. The duke <hi>Mercurie</hi> notwithſtanding hee was thus particularly intereſſed in the town of <hi>Guingand</hi> wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting neither ſufficient gariſon, munition or victuals, hauing <hi>Don Ioan de Lagula</hi> in a readineſſe with foure thouſand Spaniards at <hi>Pontiguy</hi> beſides his owne troupes: yet ſuffered this defenſible place to bee loſt without blowes vpon diſhonourable and baſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, whereby we may ſee how God rebateth the edge of rebels harts, daunteth their courages and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeth their actions with his by blows or vnlooked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for counterbuffes.</p>
            <p>That the particularities of the matter may bee better knowne vnto you, you are to vnderſtand that the town of <hi>Guingand</hi> is ſtrongly waled round about inuironed with a large ditch and a deepe counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcarfe, extending it ſelfe in length from the South Southeaſt, to the North Norweſt. Vpon the South end of the town where was ſometimes an old caſtle, there is now a very ſtrong bulwarke with three <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> and in the middeſt thereof a <hi>Cauallero</hi> which commandeth the whole towne. Not farre from it Eaſtwarde is the gate of the towne, of it ſelfe verie ſtrong, and before it a verie great <hi>Rauelin</hi> within the counterſcarfe of the ditch: at the bottom whereof there is a moſt daintie <hi>Sallye,</hi> inſomuch as a thouſand men may iſſue out at the ſame, and not one bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered
<pb facs="tcp:13634:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->vntill their heades appeare aboue the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſcarfe. And aboue them are two drawne briges for the Saliants, the one for horſe, the other for foote, &amp; right before the <hi>Raueling</hi> is a pretie conceited <hi>Turne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pike</hi> or <hi>Barricado</hi> to checke the throng and multitude of purſuers. From this place Northwarde the wall is embowed like a horne with three <hi>Flankers</hi> vpon it, and ſo ranforced within with earth, as it is accounted a <hi>Terra-pleyn.</hi> The Weſt hath a very deepe ditch ful of water: neither could any aproch be made that way by reaſon of the marriſhis. The North end of the towne hath manie <hi>Flankers</hi> and a deepe ditch, yet ſomewhat drie &amp; faſt by an Abbey of <hi>Iacopins</hi> which the villaines them ſelues pulled for the moſt part downe, leſt it ſhould anie way diſtreſſe the towne, ſtanding within leſſe then eightie paces of the towne wall. Notwithſtanding this their prouident malice, the rebels left as much ſtanding for vs as ſerued to cut their owne throates. My Lord Generall hauing quickly found that this part of the towne was fitteſt to receaue a breach, made ſhew to the quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie parte thereof, as at the South parte hee cauſed trenches to be caſt, and paſſages to be made through the walles of old houſes, euen to the verie counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcarfe of the ditch, a long trench was likewiſe caſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie neare the walles of the Eaſt ſide of the towne, and in the middeſt therof a platforme of earth to be erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſome reaſonable height, as if the canon ſhould haue beene placed there: in the meane time all trauel was vſed in making of a Mine according to our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals
<pb facs="tcp:13634:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->direction, neare to the entended breach, and the waies made for the bringing and dreſſing of the places fit for the Canon to play vpon, which was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in ſo good ſorte as that by the 20. day of this moneth our artillerie was brought downe to the <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copines</hi> cloiſter, and there placed within loſſe then an hundreth paces of the wall. And this was one of our greateſt combars both in reſpect of trauel &amp; hazard, to both which how my L. did expoſe himſelfe truely I could not but wonder, and in my hart was angry to ſee it, and yet if he had not ſo hazarded himſelfe, I did partly perceiue that little woulde haue beene done.</p>
            <p>On fryday the 21. we began our batterie, and notwithſtanding it continued all the day, yet by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the few peeces of artillerie, not able to make ſufficient batterie, the dayes worke brought forth no great effect other then the cruſhing of two <hi>Flankers,</hi> and the beating of the <hi>perrepet,</hi> ſo that the breach was very ſmall and the ſame ſo repaired continually by the ſouldiers and inhabitants within the towne, maintaining the rampart with fetherbeds, horſe dung and bags of earth almoſt to the loweſt part of their <hi>perrepet.</hi> The next day verie earely once againe wee began our batterie, and continued it vntil two or three of the clocke in the after noone, by what time the breach ſeemed verie faire. Whereupon the French humor vrged verie hotely to an aſſault, and ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned the Prince <hi>D'ombes</hi> that he conſented thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Our Generall although he was hardly drawne to yeeld his conſent, vnderſtanding by a Sergeant
<pb facs="tcp:13634:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->of a band whom he had ſent to diſcouer the breach, that the rentrenchment within was exceeding deepe, and the mounting vp the breach very ſteepe, ſliding and difficult, but eſpecially becauſe the myne was not ſo forwarde to be anſwerable to the breach: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſeeing the French men offering to attempt the place of them ſelues which had beene ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace vnto vs, yeelded to their humor, and moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly demaunded the pointe and honour of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault for the Engliſh men, which being graunted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally that they ſhoulde bee ſeconded by the French. Such was the emulation of our commanders and Captaines to winne honour, that all being wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to attempt the ſeruice, to auoide contention our Generall cauſed the dice to bee caſt, ſo that it fell to Captaine IACKSON and Captaine HERON to leade the firſt two hundreth to the aſſault, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their deuout prayers recommending them ſelues to God, they performed verie valiantly, ſcrambling vp with a notable reſolution, ſtanding a long halfe houre at the puſh of the pike in the face of a whole ſtorme of the ſmall ſhot, eſpecially Captaine IACK<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SON who came to the point of the breach, but not being throughly ſeconded by the ſouldiers vnable to get vp by reaſon of the ſteepenes of the place, yet were they hardly commanded to retire, performing their retraite with no leſſe good order then their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to the aſſault, Captaine HERON receiued a ſhot in the throate, whereof he preſently dyed, and not aboue twelue others ſlaine: Captaine IACKSON
<pb facs="tcp:13634:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->ſore hurt. Captaine WOLFE in the top of the breach had three daungerous woundes in the head, and others in his body: Captaine CATESBYE a voluntarie gentleman ſore hurt in the arme. Alſo Captaine WHITTON and Maiſter <hi>Paule Wingfeeld</hi> with ſome other yonge gentlemen to the number of 30. Which loſſe can not be thought great in ſuch a peece of ſeruice, conſidering the great ſtrength within to defend the place. The ſecond attempt was giuen by the Baron of <hi>Molac</hi> Collonel generall of the French infanterie in theſe partes, and very well anſwered by himſelfe, and ſome few of the French gentlemen, but the common ſouldiers aduancing them ſelues coldly to the breach, receiued the greater hurt, and by that occaſion were ſlaine of them many more then of our nation. Some others ſtraight pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented themſelues for a third aſſault, but the breach being found ſo difficult, and reſiſtance within ſtrong and well prepared, it was aduiſed to ſtay vntill the next day that the battery had made the breach more eaſie. During the time of the aſſault Captaine DEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIS a braue gentleman being ſent with ſome forces to make offer of a <hi>ſcalado</hi> to one other part of the towne, aduancing himſelfe too farre, receiued a Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket ſhot in the bottome of his bellie, wherof he dyed about twelue of the clocke the ſame night. That night thoſe within demanded a Parley, which being accorded, certaine deputies out of the towne repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the next morning to the Prince <hi>Dombes,</hi> and in the end grew to a capitulation, the copie whereof
<pb facs="tcp:13634:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 27 -->you ſhall receiue herein incloſed. Which in my iudgement would haue beene accorded with much more aduantage to the Prince, if he had pleaſed to haue inſiſted vpon it: but being glad to recouer the towne, which is ſaide to be the ſtrongeſt in Britanie, except <hi>Nantes</hi> and <hi>Dinant:</hi> withall doubting leaſt the Duke <hi>Mercury</hi> with the helpe of <hi>Don Iuan de Lagula</hi> ſhould come to the ſuccour of the towne, (which it is likelye had beene performed, if the French had beene in ſo good readines as the Spaniardes) he woulde not treate anie long agreement. But all thinges being accorded on both ſides, on Whitſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the towne was ſurrendered into the handes of <hi>Monſieur Cargomart</hi> appointed gouernour for the Prince. And Captaine GARGANTON which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore held the place for the Duke <hi>Mercurie,</hi> with one other named <hi>Contary,</hi> ſent by the Duke <hi>Mercurie</hi> to aſſiſt the other, departed the towne the 24. of May, with an hundred and twentie horſe, and about two hundreth and ſixtie foot, in all mens iudgement able and ſtrong enough to haue kept the place for a much longer time. We had in the towne foure Enſignes, one Cornet, one Cannon Perrier, one Demy Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering, and ſixe Sacres and Minions, two thouſand waight of pouder, and great ſtore of victuals. The hauing of this towne greatly importeth the King, for in a manner all baſe Britaine doth depend vpon it. The Courtes of Parlement, which was ordinarily held at Reynes were by the rebellious Leaguers transferred to <hi>Guingand,</hi> which argueth in what eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb facs="tcp:13634:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 27 -->they held the ſtrength of the towne. Thus haue I plainly and truly reported the ſeruice of <hi>Guin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gand,</hi> and I perceiue our Generall meaneth to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vs in action, for we are preſently to march a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Morlays</hi> a rebellious towne coaſting vpon the ſea, whereby I am enforced to leaue my penne, and betake my ſelfe to the launce, for the trompet ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>mont'a cauallo.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>Articles accorded by the Prince Dombes to the beſeeged within the towne of <hi>Guingand, in Britanie.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>1 THe Gouernour, Captaines and Souldiers of <hi>Guingand</hi> ſhal render the towne into the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces handes to morrowe the 23. of May, being Whitſonday, before noone.</item>
               <item>2 The Prince will permit that the horſemen ſhall depart the towne with their horſes and furniture, and the footemen with their Harquebuze and ſwordes by their ſide.</item>
               <item>3 The Cornets, Enſignes, and Drums which are in the towne, ſhall be deliuered to the Prince, and all their artillerie and munition of warre.</item>
               <item>4 All Engliſhmen and Iriſhmen, if there be anie, ſhall be put into the hands of the Prince.</item>
               <item>5 All Spaniards ſhall remaine priſoners.</item>
               <item>6 The gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who haue no charge of ſouldiers, who retired themſelues to the towne for refuge, ſhal pay 15000. crowns, and therby freed to enioy
<pb facs="tcp:13634:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->their poſſeſſions and mouables.</item>
               <item>7 The inhabitants of the towne ſhall pay 25000. crownes, and thereby ſhall be warranted from all pillage, enioying the kinges protection according to his late ordinances.</item>
               <item>8 The priſoners the Kinges ſeruants, ſhall be ſet at libertie, and deliuered to the Prince.</item>
               <item>9 For the aſſurance of this treatie, they ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently giue hoſtages, two for the gentlemen, two for the ſouldiers, and two for the inhabitants.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13634:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
